Moving on to spinal cord lesions, the first disorder is syringomyelia.
This is cystic degeneration of the spinal cord that can arise with trauma,
or it can also be in association with an Arnold-Chiari malformation.
It classically occurs at C8 to T1, and it results in loss of pain and temperature sensation
with sparing a fine touch and position sense in the upper extremities,
and of course in the upper extremities because we're at C8 to T1.
Now, in order to understand this, you do need to know a little bit of normal neural anatomy,
and so let's go back and remind ourselves that this is a simple spinal cord here.
Your pain and temperature sensation will actually come in from the outside.
It has a cell body here in the sensory ganglion, and then it synapses here in the posterior horn.
Now, after synapsing in the posterior horn, it sends off another nerve,
which will come down this way, cross over in the anterior white commissure,
and then come around and enter into the spinothalamic tract,
and then go up the spinothalamic tract to synapse on the thalamus.
And of course, from the thalamus, it would then synapse on the cortex.
So there's actually three independent nerves that allow pain and temperature sensation
to get to the cortex of the brain.
Now, of course, this would also be present.
So you'd have pain and temperature sensation on the opposite side of the body,
and this would also be present in the exact same way with a cell body here,
and then the nerve synapsing here, and then sending off another nerve,
which would then again also cross over in the anterior white commissure,
and come around to enter into the spinothalamic tract on the opposite side.
So what happens in syringomyelia is that you actually get a degeneration of the spinal cord here.
Of course, that's going to knock out the anterior white commissure,
and when you knock out the anterior white commissure,
you're going to knock out pain and temperature sensation on both sides.
And this knock out of pain and temperature sensation is going to occur at the level of C8 to T1,
and so the patients will have loss of pain and temperature sensation in the upper extremity.
At the same time, the dorsal column, which is back here,
which carries your fine touch and position sense, will not be altered.
And so this is the classic description of syringomyelia.
This syrinx could actually expand, and if it expands,
it could, for example, knock out the anterior horn.
Now recall that what's running in the anterior horn is going to be your motor neurons.
You have an upper motor neuron that goes from the cortex and comes down and synapses in the anterior horn,
and from the anterior horn, you have an additional neuron that goes out to the muscle.
And so if the syrinx expands and then knocks out the lower motor neuron that's going to the muscle,
you'll get signs of lower motor neuron disorder,
such as muscle weakness with atrophy, decreased tone, impaired reflexes, etc.
And so these are some of your classic lower motor neuron signs.
Now at the same time, you could take this one step further,
and the syrinx could further expand to knock out something here called the lateral horn.
So the importance of knocking out the lateral horn is that what runs through the lateral horn
is something called the hypothalamal spinal tract,
but more importantly, the hypothalamal spinal tract carries sympathetic input to the face.
Recall that in the hypothalamal spinal tract, basically you have a nerve that arises from the hypothalamus
and synapses on the lateral horn here at T1,
and then from the lateral horn, you eventually have a couple more neurons
that eventually then go and provide sympathetic input to the face.
Now if this syrinx, which of course is occurring at C8 to T1,
were to knock out the lateral horn at T1,
you would then get the classic features of Horner syndrome.
And recall that Horner syndrome basically includes ptosis, meiosis, and anhidrosis.
And again, ptosis being a droopy eyelid, meiosis being a constricted pupil,
and anhidrosis being decreased sweating of the face.
And so these are some of the other things that can occur with the syringomyelia,
and all of this is high yield because it all ties into neural anatomy.
Now I've put a little table in your book with spinal cord tracks for you to review,
but basically I've highlighted the high yields of syringomyelia with the image that I've drawn here.
So we say that it usually occurs at C8 to T1, therefore it's going to involve the upper extremity.
You get loss of pain and temperature sensation with sparing a fine touch and position sense.
If it expands, you'll get involvement of other tracks,
and this could knock out the anterior horn,
resulting in a lower motor neuron problem with muscle atrophy with weakness,
decreased tone and impaired reflexes.
And at the same time, if it further expands, you can also knock out the lateral horn.
And when you knock out the lateral horn, you're going to knock out the sympathetic input to the face,
giving you ptosis, meiosis, and anhidrosis.
Moving on to the next disorder, poliomyelitis is damaged to the anterior motor horn due to a poliovirus infection.
Let's go back and remind ourselves that polio has a fecal-oral transmission.
Polio then infects the oropharynx and the small bowel.
That gives you fevers, sore throat, abdominal pain with nausea and vomiting.
And then it can eventually spread to the CNS via the blood.
Now, when it spreads to the CNS via the blood, it eventually gets into the anterior motor horn,
and that's where it causes its damage.
So, again, if you draw a simple spinal cord,
then the problem is you've knocked out the anterior motor horn here.
And, of course, from the anterior motor horn was coming the neuron that was going to go out to the skeletal muscle.
And so you're going to knock out the lower motor neuron.
Now, when you knock out the lower motor neuron, you get flaccid paralysis with muscle atrophy.
You get weakness with decreased tone.
You get impaired reflexes.
And you get a negative Babinski sign, i.e., downward-going toes.
The same exact thing can occur in a disorder called Wurndig-Hoffman disease.
However, instead of it being due to polio, it's due to an inherited degeneration of the anterior motor horn.
This is autosomal recessive, and it presents as a floppy baby.
And here I've described this in your text by telling you that you get an inherited degeneration of the anterior motor horn.
Again, this is autosomal recessive, floppy baby, and death occurs within a few years after birth.
Amyotrophic lateral sclerosis is a degenerative disorder of upper and lower motor neurons.
You get degeneration of the anterior motor horn, which then leads to lower motor neuron signs.
So the lower motor neuron signs include flaccid paralysis with muscle atrophy, you get fasciculations, weakness with decreased tone, impaired reflexes, and a negative Babinski.
So it's as if everything kind of decreases, where you have this flaccid paralysis with decreased tone, with impaired reflexes, and downward-going toes.
And because you involve the lateral corticospinal tract, that leads to upper motor neuron signs.
And with upper motor neuron signs, you get spastic paralysis with hyperreflexia, increased muscle tone, and upward-going toes.
So it's as if things go up.
And this is the key summary for board examination purposes, i.e., upper and lower motor neuron signs.
Now, this can somewhat resemble syringomyelia, because recall that syringomyelia involves C8 to T1, and so it would involve the upper extremities and could involve the hands.
And in syringomyelia, you could have damage to the anterior horn, and so that could also result in atrophy and weakness of the hands.
However, of course, in syringomyelia, you're going to have loss of pain and temperature sensation, whereas in amyotrophic lateral sclerosis, you would have no loss of pain or temperature sensation.
And so this is an important distinction between ALS and syringomyelia.
Now, most cases of ALS are sporadic, arising in middle-aged adults.
However, one very high-yield point for the purposes of board exams is that in familial cases, there can be a zinc-copper superoxide dismutase mutation.
And that's very high-yield, because recall that superoxide dismutase is an important mechanism of removing free radicals.
Remember that oxygen has the ability to produce superoxide-free radical, and that free radical would be converted to hydrogen peroxide by superoxide dismutase.
Now, if you lose superoxide dismutase, you're going to have increased free radical damage within the cells.
And so in this particular case, free radical injury could lead to damage in the neurons, and examiners love to go after that.
Friedrich ataxia is a degenerative disorder of the cerebellum and spinal cord tracts.
Because the cerebellum's involved, you get ataxia, hence the word ataxia in the name.
And also, because the spinal cord tracts are involved, you get loss of vibratory sense and proprioception.
You get muscle weakness in the lower extremities, loss of the deep tendon reflexes.
So the key thing here is ataxia plus multiple spinal cord tracts.
Now, this is an autosomal recessive disorder characterized by an unstable trinucleotide repeat in the frataxin gene.
High-yield to note, the frataxin gene is essential for mitochondrial iron regulation.
And, of course, if you cannot regulate iron properly, you increase the risk of developing free radicals via the fentanyl reaction.
And so, again, here you would also get free radical damage to the neurons.
Now, this presents an early childhood.
And another high-yield dissociation is that these patients can have hypertrophic cardiomyopathy.
Examiners like to go after that as well.
And that concludes our discussion of spinal cord lesions.